Hello everyone and welcome to
English Pod, my name is Marco.
My name is Catherine and we're
in the mood to read something
today so we're going to a
place called the library, right?
That's right, we're going to go to the
library and we're going to get some books.
But before we do that, let's take a
look at a word in vocabulary preview.
Very capillary preview.
All right, so today's vocabulary
preview word is a thing that
you use when you go to the
library to take that book home.
You don't have to pay for the book,
you use your library card to borrow it.
That's right.
So this is something that
you need when you want to
get books at the library,
you need a library card.
So we're going to talk about
this and how you get a library card.
So let's listen to the dialogue.
Wow, look at all these books.
I bet I can find a book
about anything here.
Please keep your voice down, there
are people reading and studying here.
Okay, I'm sorry, are you the librarian?
Maybe you can help me.
I am looking for a book.
Yes, I am.
You can check our
online catalog, the search
for the book you want
based on the genre
title or if you know the author, I can
point you towards the right direction.
I'm looking for a book
that has nursery rhymes.
That would be in our children section,
that bookshelf there on the right.
Okay, I would like to
check out these books.
Do you have a library card?
No.
How do I get one?
I just need to see
a driver's license or
utility bill to prove that you
are a resident of this state.
Here you go.
So you're all set.
You can have these books for two weeks.
If you need to have them longer,
you can bring them here to renew them.
If you don't, you get charged
10 cents a day for each book.
Okay, thanks.
All right, we're back, so now
let's start with language take away.
Language take away.
All right, we have a lot of great things
for you today in language take away.
The first is actually a job.
This is a person who works at a
library and what's that person called?
He or she is called a librarian.
All right, so someone who
works at a library is a librarian.
That's right.
So this person organizes
the books, knows about
all the books that are there and
basically takes care of the library.
That's right.
Up in the library, it's
probably a good idea
to ask the librarian where
the book you're looking for is.
That's right.
And today we went in looking
for a specific type of book.
We wanted a book that had nursery rhymes.
All right, nursery rhymes.
Now these are kind
of like songs or poems,
things that we tell little
children and babies.
So Mary had a little lamb, little
lamb, that that is a nursery rhyme.
It's a it's a playful poem for children.
That's right.
So obviously since we
are looking for nursery
rhyme books, the librarian told us that
we need to go to the children's section.
That's right.
But before we get to
borrow this book, there
are a couple of things we need because
the person doesn't have a library card.
Now the question is,
how do I get a library card?
What was the librarians response Marco?
Well, it was pretty simple.
All we needed was to see that person's
driver's license or a utility bill.
All right, so a
driver's license is an ID
card and identification card that
you get that allows you to drive a car.
Now each state has
a different kind of
driver's license and different
rules for how to get one.
But this is a very common, almost the most
common kind of identification in America.
That's right.
So basically you show
them your driver's
license and it has a
picture of you there,
your telephone number
and even your address.
That's right.
But not everybody has a driver's license.
Some people don't drive, some people can't
drive, some people don't want to drive.
So they would have to show something else.
And a good way to show that you live
somewhere is to show your utility bill.
That's right.
So a utility is basically water,
electricity, gas, or your telephone bill.
And it arrives to your
house and that's where
it's, well, obviously it says your address
there and who the bill is directed to.
So you can prove that you live there.
That's right, because why would somebody
else pay for the water at that house?
It's obviously used.
So these are a couple kinds of identification
you can use to get a library card.
All right.
And while we're taking the books,
we can borrow them for two weeks.
But if we need to have
them for a longer period
of time, we can take them back to
the library and have them renewed.
So to renew something, renew
means to continue to borrow it.
You have to re borrow,
we don't say re bar, we
say renews, that means we
get it for another two weeks.
That's right.
So things that expire
usually you need to
renew like for example,
your driver's license.
Usually it will last
maybe five years, but
then you need to renew
your driver's license.
And if you don't
renew it, if you forget to
renew something, maybe
there'll be a problem
like in the case of the library,
you have to pay for the late fees.
Your book is overdue, you have to pay for
it, or in the case of a driver's license,
if your driver's license is overdue,
well, you probably have to get a new one.
That's right.
Okay.
So a lot of vocab there, why don't we
review everything and we'll be right back.
Wow, look at all these books.
I bet I can find a book
about anything here.
Please keep your voice down, there
are people reading and studying here.
Okay, I'm sorry, are you the librarian?
Maybe you can help me,
I am looking for a book.
Yes, I am.
You can check our
online catalog to search
for the book you want
based on the genre title
or if you know the author, I can
point you towards the right direction.
I'm looking for a book
that has nursery rhymes,
that would be in our children's
section, a book shelf there on the right.
Okay, I would like to
check out these books.
Do you have a library card?
No, how do I get one?
I just need to see
a driver's license or
utility bill to prove that you
are a resident of this state.
Here you go.
So you're all set.
You can have these books for two weeks.
If you need to have them longer,
you can bring them here to renew them.
If you don't, you get charged
10 cents a day for each book.
Okay, thanks.
All right, so now we have three key
phrases for you on fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
So Marco, what are librarians famous for?
Well librarians are always telling
you to please keep your voice down.
All right, so librarians
are quiet places,
they're places where people like
to go and read and think and study.
So oftentimes when
people are talking, they're
being loud, the librarian will say,
hey, keep your voice down or be quiet.
That's right.
So another way of saying,
be quiet is keep your
voice down and it's
a little bit more polite.
Please keep your voice down.
Keep your voice down.
Or if there's two people or three
people, you'd say, keep your voices down.
So the librarian tells
us to keep our voice
down and, well, now we
can get some help from
the librarian and he
says that, you know, if
you know the title of
the book or the genre
or the name of the author, the librarian
can point you towards the right direction.
Now to point someone
in the right direction
or point someone
towards the right direction
means to help them
understand where to go.
Maybe they don't know exactly
the title of the book or the author.
But in this case, the librarian can
help put the person in the right place.
So I can point you in the right direction
or point you towards the right direction.
Exactly.
Even maybe you're lost in a town and you
stop and ask someone for directions because
you don't know how
to get there and that
person can help you by pointing
you towards the right direction.
All right.
This means I can help you.
Basically.
And now what we wanted to do was we
wanted to borrow books from the library.
We wanted to get books from the library.
But we have another way of saying this.
We can say we want to check out some books.
All right.
So to check out a book means to borrow
it, like you say, but this is also a noun.
Check out.
That's the place where you scan something.
So maybe there's a bar, a black
bar on the back of the book.
When you scan it, it
scans out, that means that
you're borrowing it, you get it
for two weeks and you bring it back.
Check it out.
Okay.
So a lot of great
stuff in this dialogue
today learning about libraries
and how to get a library card.
Why don't we review
everything one last time?
Wow.
Look at all these books.
I bet I can find a book
about anything here.
Please keep your voice down.
There are people reading and studying here.
Okay.
I'm sorry.
Are you the librarian?
Maybe you can help me.
I am looking for a book.
Yes, I am.
You can check our
online catalog to search
for the book you want
based on the genre title
or if you know the author, I can
point you towards the right direction.
I'm looking for a book
that has nursery rhymes.
That would be in our children's section.
A book shelf there on the right.
Okay, I would like to
check out these books.
Do you have a library card?
No.
How do I get one?
I just need to see
a driver's license or
utility bill to prove that you
are a resident of this state.
Here you go.
So you're all set.
You can have these books for two weeks.
If you need to have them longer,
you can bring them here to renew them.
If you don't, you can get charged
10 cents a day for each book.
Okay.
Thanks.
Alright, so borrowing
books in a library
seems pretty simple
and you don't really have
to leave a deposit or something just in
case you steal the book or you damage it.
How do you deal with this?
No.
Libraries are a wonderful part
of, well at least American culture.
I'm not really sure
how they work in other
places, but in America there's a
lot of federal money in libraries.
In fact, I think it was
Franklin Roosevelt
who really helps get a library
system in place in America.
So they're a part of this system of kind
of community sharing and information.
You can go to the
library and look for jobs.
They have computers.
Many have DVD and video sections.
Many have very wonderful CD sections.
So basically it's a community
center for information, knowledge.
It's almost a relationship with trust.
I trust that the library
will provide for me and
the library will trust that
I don't destroy a book.
Of course, if you do, you have to pay.
We have to pay.
So is it a federal offense to
steal a book from a library?
I don't know, but it's a pretty big
deal to steal a book from the library.
They certainly will know
who you are because
they have your information,
your driver's license.
Right.
It's actually pretty
interesting, especially
because as you said, there's a
lot of money put into libraries.
So it's all communities
have them as you say
DVDs or movies or a lot
of different types of books.
And in other countries,
like maybe in Latin
America, it's not as popular
to have a community library.
We can go and check things out because
there's not that much money involved as well.
But we would be curious to
know how it works in your country.
Maybe your country has some
beautiful or extensive libraries.
Yeah.
I'm very curious as well.
So public libraries do you have them?
And if you don't, do you also have
university libraries you can go to?
Let us know our website is EnglishPod.com.
All right, guys.
We'll see you there.
Bye.